<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three sermons preached 1. In Whitehall, March 29. being the first Tuesday after the departure of King Iames into blessednesse. 2. In Christs Church, at the trienniall visitation of the right Reuerend Father in God, the Lord Bishop of London. 3. In the chappell by Guildhall, at the solemne election of the Right Honourable the Lord Maior of London. / By Tho: Adams.</title>
            <author>Adams, Thomas, fl. 1612-1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68162</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 130</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S122193</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857345</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857345</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23065</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68162)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23065)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1163:4 or 1699:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three sermons preached 1. In Whitehall, March 29. being the first Tuesday after the departure of King Iames into blessednesse. 2. In Christs Church, at the trienniall visitation of the right Reuerend Father in God, the Lord Bishop of London. 3. In the chappell by Guildhall, at the solemne election of the Right Honourable the Lord Maior of London. / By Tho: Adams.</title>
                  <author>Adams, Thomas, fl. 1612-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 79, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Aug. Matthewes, and Iohn Norton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A sermon preached at the trienniall visitation of the Right Reuerend Father in God, the Lord Bishop of London, in Christ-Church" and "The holy choice" each have separate dated title page, the former on E2v; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>"The holy choice" identified as STC 123 at reel 1163:4.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library and Harvard University. Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 1163 (Folger Shakespeare Library, "The holy choice" only) and at reel 1699 (Harvard University Library copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:23065:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23065:1"/>
            <p>THE HOLY CHOICE. A SERMON PREACHED in the Chappell by GVILDHALL, <hi>at the Solemnitie of the Election</hi> of the Right Honourable the <hi>Lord Maior of</hi> LONDON.</p>
            <p>BY THO: ADAMS.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Aug. Matthewes,</hi> and <hi>John Norton.</hi> 1625.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:23065:2"/>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:23065:2"/>
            <head>THE HOLY CHOICE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ACTES 1.24.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And they prayed, and ſaid, Thou Lord, which know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt the hearts of all men, ſhew whether of theſe two thou hast choſen.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He buſineſſe of the day is an <hi>Election;</hi> an election into one of the moſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Offices of the Kingdome; the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of this Honourable Citie, which (let not enuie heare it) hath no paralell vnder the Sunne. The buſineſſe of my Text is an <hi>Election</hi> too; an election into the higheſt office in the Church, to be an <hi>Apoſtle</hi> and <hi>Witneſſe</hi> of Ieſus Chriſt. If you pleaſe to ſpare the paterne in foure circumſtances; as, 1. This office is ſpiritual, yours temporall. 2. This place was voyd by A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaſie or deceſſion, yours is ſupplied by ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. 3. This election is by Lots, yours is by Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages. 4. This choice was but one of two, it may be your number exceeds: the reſt will ſure well enough, and the ſame God that was in the one, be alſo preſent in the other, by the aſſiſtance of his holy ſpirit.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:23065:3"/>
            <p> The argument of the Text is a prayer to God for his direction in their choice: yea indeed, that hee would chuſe a man for them: including a ſtrong reaſon of ſuch a requeſt, becauſe he doth <hi>know the hearts of all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They begin with <hi>prayer;</hi> this was the vſuall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in the Church of God. So <hi>Moſes</hi> prayed for the choice of his Succeſſor.
<note place="margin">Num. 27.16.</note> 
               <hi>Let the Lord, the God of the ſpirits of all fleſh ſet a man ouer the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Chriſt ſent not his Apoſtles to that holy work,
<note place="margin">Iohn 17.27.</note> without a prayer; <hi>Sanctifie them through thy truth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Actes 6.6.</note> In the chuſing of thoſe ſeuen Deacons, they firſt prayed, and then <hi>laid their hands vpon them.</hi> Thus were Kings Inaugurated, with <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> and <hi>Prayer.</hi> It is not fit, he that is choſen for God, ſhould bee choſen without God. But for this, <hi>Samuel</hi> himſelfe may be miſtaken, and chuſe ſeuen wrong, before hee hit vpon the right. In this; I cannot but commend your religious care; that buſineſſes of ſo great a conſequence be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſanctified with a bleſſing. Thoſe which in a due proportion, muſt repreſent God to the world, ought to be conſecrated to that Maieſtie which they reſemble, by publike deuotions. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery important action requires <hi>Prayer,</hi> much more that which concernes a whole citie. When <hi>Samuel</hi> came to <hi>Bethlehem</hi> to annoynt <hi>Dauid,</hi> he calls the whole Citie to the Sacrifice. Indeed the Family of <hi>Ieſſe</hi> was ſanctified in a more ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall manner: this buſineſſe was moſt theirs, and all Iſraels in them. The feare of God ſhould take full poſſeſſion of all our hearts, that are this day
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:23065:3"/>aſſembled: but thoſe with whom God hath more to doe then with the reſt, ſhould bee more holy then the reſt.</p>
            <p>The choice of your Wardens and Maſters in your ſeuerall Companies hath a ſolemne forme; and it is the honour of your greateſt Feaſts, that the firſt diſh is a Sermon. Charitie forbid, that any ſhould think, you admit ſuch a Cuſtome, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for conuenience then deuotion; as if Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching were but a neceſſary complement to a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnitie, as Wine and Muſicke. I am perſwaded better things of you: but if there ſhould be any ſuch peruerſe ſpirits, that like the Gouernor of a people called <hi>Aequi,</hi> when the Romans came to him, <hi>Iuſsit eos ad quercum dicere,</hi> bade them ſpeak to the Oake, for he had other buſineſſe: but they replied, <hi>Et haec ſacrata quercus audiat foedus a vobis violatum;</hi> let this Oake beare witneſſe, that you haue broke the league which you haue couenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. So when we come to preach to your ſoules, if you ſhould ſecretly bid vs ſpeake to the walls; loe euen the very walls will be witneſſes againſt you at the laſt day. Though <hi>Saul</hi> be King ouer <hi>Samuel,</hi> yet <hi>Samuel</hi> muſt teach <hi>Saul</hi> how to bee King. Wee may inſtruct, though wee may not rule; yea, wee muſt inſtruct them that ſhall rule. Therefore as wee obey your call in comming to ſpeake, ſo doe you obey Gods command in vouchſafing to heare. Let vs apply our ſelues to him with deuotion, and then hee will bee graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly preſent at our Election.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:23065:4"/>
            <p> This Prayer reſpects two things,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Quem,</hi> the perſon whom they intreat.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Quid,</hi> the matter for which they intreat</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Perſon is deſcribed by His
<list>
                  <item>Omnipotence; <hi>Lord.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Omniſcience, <hi>That knoweſt the hearts of men.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Omnipotence; Lord. Wee acknowledge thy right, thou art fit to bee thine owne chuſer. <hi>Lord,</hi> there bee many on earth called Lords; but thoſe are Lords of earth, and thoſe Lords are earth, &amp; thoſe Lords muſt returne to earth. This Lord is Almightie; raiſing out of the duſt to the honour of Princes, and <hi>laying the honour of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the duſt. Lord,</hi> of what? nay, not qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; not Lord of ſuch a Countie, Barony, Seigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orie; nor Lord by vertue of Office and Deputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but <hi>in abſtracte,</hi> moſt abſolute: His <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> is vniuerſall: <hi>Lord</hi> of heauen, the owner of thoſe glorious manſions: <hi>Lord</hi> of earth, diſpoſer of all Kingdomes and Principalities: <hi>Lord</hi> of hell, to locke vp the old Dragon and his crew in the bottomleſſe pit: <hi>Lord</hi> of Death, to vnlocke the graues: hee keepes the Key, that ſhall let all bodies out of their earthy priſons. A potent <hi>Lord;</hi> whither ſhall we goe to get out of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion?
<note place="margin">Pſal. 139.7. &amp;c</note> To heauen? there wee cannot miſſe him: To hell? there wee cannot bee without him: In ayre, earth, or ſea; in light or darkneſſe, wee are ſure to finde him. Whither then, except to Purgatory? That <hi>Terra incognita</hi> is not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in his <hi>Lordſhip:</hi> the Pope may keepe the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:23065:4"/>key of that himſelfe. But for the reſt, hee is too ſawcie; exalting his vniuerſal Lordſhip, and hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging in the whole Chriſtian world for his Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. Stretching his arme to heauen, in rubric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king what Saints he liſt: to hell, in freeing what priſoners hee liſt: on earth, in ſetting vp, or pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling downe what Kings hee liſt: but that ſome haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhort his buſie fingers.</p>
            <p>To the <hi>Lord</hi> of all they commend the choyce of his owne ſeruants. Euery mortall Lord hath this power in his owne Family: how much more that <hi>Lord,</hi> which makes Lords? who is ſo fit to chuſe, as he that can chuſe the fit? Who ſo fit to chuſe, as hee that can make thoſe fit whom he doth chuſe? It is He alone that can giue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and grace to the elected, therefore not to be left out in the election. How can the Apoſtle preach, or the Magiſtrate gouerne, without him; when none of vs all can mooue but in him? It is happy, when wee doe remit all doubts to his deciſion, and reſigne our ſelues to his diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Wee muſt not be our owne Caruers, but let Gods choyce be ours. When we know his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, let vs ſhew our obedience. And for you, vpon whom this Election falls, remember how you are bound to honour that Lord of heauen, that hath ordained ſuch honour for you vpon earth: that ſo in all things wee may glorifie his bleſſed Name.</p>
            <p>Omniſcience: it is Gods peculiar, to bee the ſearcher of the heart. <hi>The heart of man is deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full aboue all things, and deſperately wicked; who
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:23065:5"/>can know it?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 17.9.10.</note> Who? <hi>Ego Dominus, I the Lord ſearch the heart.</hi> Hee hath made no window in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, for man or Angel, to looke in: onely it hath a doore, and he keepes the key himſelfe.</p>
            <p>But why the <hi>Heart?</hi> Here was an Apoſtle to bee choſen: now wiſdome, learning, eloquence, memorie, might ſeeme to bee more neceſſary qualities, then the <hi>Heart.</hi> No, they are all no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to an honeſt <hi>Heart.</hi> I denie not, but Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to diuide the Word, Elocution to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce it, Wiſdome to diſcerne the truth, Bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to deliuer it, bee all parts requireable in a Preacher. But as if all theſe were ſcarſe worth mention in reſpect of the <hi>Heart;</hi> they ſay not, Thou that knoweſt which of them hath the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiler wit, or abler memory; but which hath the truer heart: not which is the greater Scholer, but which is the better man; <hi>Thou that knowest the Heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Samuel</hi> being ſent to annoynt a ſonne of <hi>Ieſſe,</hi> when <hi>Eliab,</hi> the eldeſt came foorth, a man of a goodly preſence, fit for his perſon to ſucceed <hi>Saul;</hi> he thinkes with himſelfe, This choyce is ſoone made, ſure this is the head vpon which I muſt ſpend my holy Oyle. The priuiledge of Nature and of Stature, his primogeniture and proportion giues it him; This is hee. But euen the holyeſt Prophet, when hee ſpeakes without God, runnes into errour. Signes and apparances are the guides of our eyes; and theſe are ſeldome without a true falſhood, or an vncertaine truth. <hi>Saul</hi> had a goodly perſon, but a bad heart: hee
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:23065:5"/>was higher then all, many were better then hee. It is not hard for the beſt Iudgement to erre in the ſhape. <hi>Philoxemenes,</hi> a magnanimous and valiant Souldier, being inuited to <hi>Magyas</hi> his houſe to dinner, came in due ſeaſon, but found not his Hoſt at home. A ſeruant ſeeing one ſo plaine in clothes, and ſomewhat defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in bodie, thought him ſome ſorry fellow, and ſet him to cleaue wood. Whereat <hi>Magyas</hi> (being returned) wondering, he receiued from him this anſwere; <hi>Expendo paenas deformitatis meae;</hi> I pay for my vnhandſomneſſe. All is not valour, that lookes bigge, and goes braue. Hee that iudgeth by the inſide, checked <hi>Samuel</hi> for his miſconceit;
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 16.7.</note> 
               <hi>Looke not on his Countenance or Stature, for I haue refuſed him: for the Lord ſeeth not as man ſeeth. Dauids</hi> countenance was inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous and beautifull, but had it promiſed ſo much as <hi>Eliabs</hi> or <hi>Abinadabs,</hi> hee had not been left in the field, while his Brethren ſate at the table. <hi>Ieſſe</hi> could find nothing in <hi>Dauid</hi> worthy the competition of honour with his brethren: God could finde ſomething to preferre him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them all. His father thought him fit to keepe ſheepe, thought his Brethren fit to rule men. God thinkes him fit to rule, and his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to ſerue; and by his owne immediate choyce deſtines him to the Throne. Here was all the difference; <hi>Samuel</hi> and <hi>Ieſſe</hi> went by the outſide, God by the inſide: they ſaw the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the body, hee the diſpoſition of the mind. Iſrael deſires a King of God, and that
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:23065:6"/>King was choſen by the Head: God will chuſe a King for Iſrael, and that King is choſen by the <hi>Heart.</hi> If in our choyce for God, or for our ſelues, wee altogether follow the eye, and ſuffer our thoughts to be guided by outward reſpects, we ſhall be deceiued.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Why doe they not ſay, <hi>Thou that knoweſt</hi> the eſtates of men, who is rich, and fit to ſupport a high place; and who ſo poore that the place muſt ſupport him? I heare ſome call <hi>Wealth, Subſtance;</hi> but certainly at beſt, it is but a meere circumſtance. It is like the Planet <hi>Mercury;</hi> if it bee ioyned with a good <hi>Heart,</hi> it is vſefull; if with a bad and corrupt one, dangerous. But howſoeuer at the Beame of the Sanctuary, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney makes not the man, yet it often addes ſome mettall to the man; makes his Iuſtice the bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and in leſſe hazard of being vitiated. But <hi>pauperis ſapientia plus valet quam diuitis abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantia.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.13.</note> If the poore man haue <hi>Wiſedome to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the Citie,</hi> hee is worthy to gouerne the Citie. I yeeld, that ſomething is due to the State of Authoritie; <hi>Ad populum Phaleras:</hi> So <hi>Agrippa</hi> came to the Tribunall with great pompe and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance. This is requiſite to keepe awe in the people, that the Magiſtracie bee not expoſed to contempt. But <hi>Magiſtratus, non veſtitus, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicat virum:</hi> Wiſe gouernment, not rich gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhewes an able man. It was not riches, that they regarded.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Why doe they not ſay, <hi>Thou that knoweſt</hi> the Birth or Blood of men? I know, it is a reuerend
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:23065:6"/>thing to ſee an ancient Caſtle or Palace not in decay; or a faire Tree, ſound and perfect tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. But as foule Birds build their neſts in an olde forſaken houſe, and doated trees are good for nothing but the fire; ſo the decay of Vertue is the ruine of Nobilitie. To ſpeake morally, Actiue worth is better then Paſſiue; this laſt we haue from our Anceſtors, the firſt from our ſelues. Let mee rather ſee one vertue in a man aliue, then all the reſt in his pedigree dead. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is regular in the bruite Creatures; Eagles doe not produce crauens; and it was a monſtrous fable, that <hi>Nicippus</hi> his Ewe ſhould yeane a Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But in man ſhee failes, and may bring forth the like proportion, not the like diſpoſition. Children doe often reſemble their Parents in face and features, not in heart and qualities. It is the earthly part that followes the ſeed; wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, valour, vertue, are of another begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Honour ſits beſt vpon the backe of merit: I had rather bee good without Honour, then Honourable without goodneſſe. Cottages haue yeelded this as well as Palaces. <hi>Agathocles</hi> was the ſonne of a Potter, <hi>Bion</hi> of an infamous Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſan. In holy Writ, <hi>Gideon</hi> was a poore Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher, <hi>Dauid</hi> a Shepheard; yet both mightie men of valour, both choſen to rule, both ſpeciall Sauiours of their Countrey. Farre bee it from vs to condemne all honour of the firſt head, when noble deſeruings haue raiſed it; though before it could ſhewe nothing but a White Shield. Indeed, it is not the Birth, but the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:23065:7"/>new Birth, that makes men truely Noble.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Why doe they not ſay, <hi>Thou that knoweſt</hi> the wiſedome and policie of men? Certainly, this is requiſite to a man of place; without which hee is a blinde <hi>Polyphemus,</hi> a ſtrong arme with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an eye. But a man may bee wiſe for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, not for God, not for the publike good. An Ante is a wiſe creature for it ſelfe, but a ſhrewd thing in a Garden. Magiſtrates, that are great louers of themſelues, are ſeldome true louers of their Countrey. All their actions bee motions, that haue recourſe to one Center, that is, themſelues. A cunning head without an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt heart, is but like him that can packe the Cards, yet when hee hath done, cannot play the Game, or like a houſe with many conuenient Staires, Entries, and other paſſages, but neuer a faire roome; all the inwards bee ſluttiſh and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue. It is not then, <hi>Thou that knoweſt</hi> the Wealth, or the Birth, or the Head, but the <hi>Heart;</hi> as if in an Election, that were the maine; it is all if the reſt be admitted on the By.</p>
            <p>Heere then wee haue three remarkeable ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations. 1. What kind of Hearts God will not chuſe, and we may gueſſe at them. 2. What Hearts hee will chuſe, and himſelfe deſcribes them. 3. Why hee will chuſe men eſpecially by the Heart.</p>
            <p>Firſt what kind of Hearts hee will not chuſe; and of theſe (among many) I will mention but three.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Cor diuiſum,</hi> a diſtracted Heart; part wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:23065:7"/>is dedicated to the Lord, and part to the world. But hee that made all, will not bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with a piece. <hi>Aut Caeſar, aut nihil.</hi> The ſeruice of two Maſters, in the obedience of their contrary commands, is incompetible, <hi>ſenſu com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſito.</hi> Indeed <hi>Zacheus</hi> did firſt ſerue the world, and not Chriſt; afterward Chriſt, and not the world; but neuer the world and Chriſt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Many diuiſions followed ſinne. 1. It di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided the heart from God;
<note place="margin">Eſai. 59.2.</note> 
               <hi>Your ſinnes haue ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated betweene you and your God.</hi> 2. It diuided heart from heart. God by Marriage made one of two, ſinne doth often by preuarication make two of one. It diuided the tongue from the heart. So <hi>Cain</hi> anſwered God, when hee que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned him about <hi>Abel; Am I my Brothers kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per?</hi> As if hee would ſay, Goe looke. 4. It di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided tongue from tongue, at the building of <hi>Babell;</hi> that when one called for Bricke, his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low brings him morter: and when hee ſpake of comming downe, the other falles a remoouing the ladder. 5. It diuided the heart from it ſelfe; <hi>They ſpake with a double heart.</hi> The originall is,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 12.2.</note> 
               <hi>A heart and a heart:</hi> one for the Church, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the Change: one for Sundayes, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for working dayes: one for the King, an other for the Pope. A man without a heart, is a wonder: but a man with two hearts, is a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. It is ſaid of <hi>Iudas,</hi> There were many hearts in one man: and wee read of the Saints, There was one heart in many men. <hi>Dabo illis cor vnum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Actes 4.32.</note> a ſpeciall bleſſing.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:23065:8"/>
            <p> Now this diuiſion of heart is intolerable in a Magiſtrate; when hee plyes his owne cauſe vnder the pretence of anothers; and cares not who loſe, ſo hee bee a gayner. Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> calles this <hi>Cor malè locatum;</hi> for many haue hearts, but not in their right places. <hi>Cor habet in ventre guloſus, laſciuus in libidine, cupidus in lucris.</hi> Naturally, if the heart bee remooued from the proper ſeare, it inſtantly dyes. The eye vnneſted from the head, cannot ſee: the foote ſundered from the body, cannot goe: ſo ſpiritually, let the heart bee vncentred from Chriſt, it is dead. Thus the Coward is ſayd to haue his heart at his heele, the timorous hath his heart at his mouth, the enuious hath his heart in his eyes, the Prodigall hath his heart in his hand, the foole hath his heart in his tongue, the couetous locks it vp in his cheſt. He that <hi>knowes the hearts of all men,</hi> will not chuſe a diuided or miſplaced heart.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Cor lapideum,</hi> a hard or ſtony heart. This is <hi>Ingratum ad beneficia, infidum ad conſilia, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verecundum ad turpia, inhumanum ad bona, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merarium ad omnia.</hi> A Rocke, which all the Floods of that infinite Sea of Gods mercies and Iudgements cannot ſoften. A Stitthy, that is ſtill the harder for beating. It hath all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of a ſtone: it is as cold as a ſtone, as hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie as a ſtone, as hard as a ſtone, as ſenſeleſſe as a ſtone. No perſwaſions can heate it, no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitions can ſtay it, no inſtructions can teach it, no compaſſions can mollifie it. Were it of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:23065:8"/>yron, it might bee wrought: were it of lead, it might bee molten, and caſt into ſome better forme: were it of earth, it might bee tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to another faſhion: but being ſtone, nothing remaines but that it bee broken. What was <hi>Pharaohs</hi> greateſt plague? was it the murraine of Beaſtes? was it the plague of Boyles? was it the deſtruction of the Fruits? was it the turning of their Riuers into Blood? was it the ſtriking of their Firſt borne with death? No, though all theſe plagues were grieuous, yet one was more grieuous then all; <hi>Cor durum,</hi> his hard heart. Hee that <hi>knowes all hearts,</hi> knowes how ill this would be in a Magiſtrate: a heart, which no cryes of Orphans, no teares of Widowes, no mourning of the oppreſſed, can melt into pitie. From ſuch a Heart good Lord deliuer vs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Cor eupidum,</hi> a couetous heart; the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires whereof are neuer filled. A handfull of corne put to the whole heape, encreaſeth it; yea, adde water to the Sea, it hath ſo much the more: but <hi>hee that loueth Siluer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ 5.10.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall neuer bee ſatisfied with Siluer.</hi> One deſire may bee filled, but ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther comes. <hi>Creſcit amor nummi, quantùm ipſa pecunia creſeit.</hi> Naturall deſires are finite, as thirſt is ſatisfied with drinke, and hunger with meate. But vnnatuall deſires bee infinite; as it fares with the body in burning Feuers; <hi>Quò plus ſunt potae, plus ſitiuntur aquae:</hi> So it is in the couetous heart, <hi>Vt cùm poſideat plurimae, plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra petaet.</hi> Grace can neuer fill the purſe, nor wealth the heart.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:23065:9"/>
            <p> This vice is in all men iniquitie, but in a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate Blaſphemie: the roote of all euill in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man, the rot of all goodneſſe in a great Man. It leaues them, like thoſe Idoles in the Pſalme; neither eyes to ſee, nor eares to heare; but onely hands to handle. Such men will tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe for handfulls of barley, and morſells of bread; and a very dramme of profite put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Scole of Iuſtice, turnes it to the wrong ſide. There is not among all the charmes of Hell, a more damnable ſpell to inchant a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, then the loue of Money. This <hi>turnes Iudgement into Wormewood,</hi> or at leaſt into vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: for if Iniuſtice doe not make it bitter as Wormewood, yet ſhifts and delayes will make it ſowre as vineger. O how ſordid and execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſhould bribes bee to them, and ſtinke worſe in their noſtrils then <hi>Veſpaſians</hi> tribute of vrine! Let them not onely binde their owne hands, and the hands of their ſeruants, that may take; but euen binde the hands of them that would offer. Hee that vſeth Integritie, doeth the former: but hee that conſtantly profeſſeth Integritie, doth the latter. It is not enough to auoyde the fault, but euen the ſuſpition: It is ſome diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to the Iudge, when a Clyent with his bribe comes to bee denyed: for if his vſuall carriage had giuen him no hope of ſpeeding, hee would not offer. A Seruant, that is a fauourite or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, giues ſuſpition of corruption, and is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly thought but a by-way; ſome poſterne or back-dore for a gift to come in, when the broad
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:23065:9"/>fore-gates are ſhut againſt it. This makes many aſpire to Offices and great places, not to doe good, but to get goods; as ſome loue to bee ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the fire, if it bee but to warme their owne fingers. Whatſoeuer affaires paſſe through their hands, they crooke them all to their owne endes; and care not what becomes of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like good, ſo they may aduance their owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate: and would ſet their neighbours houſe on fire, and it were but to roſt their owne egges. Let them baniſh Couetouſneſſe, with as great a hatred as <hi>Amnon</hi> did <hi>Thamar;</hi> firſt thruſt it out of their hearts, then ſhut and locke the dore after it: for the couetous heart is none of them that God chuſeth.</p>
            <p>Next let vs ſee what kinde of hearts God will chuſe; and they be furniſhed with theſe vertues fit for a Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is <hi>Cor ſapiens,</hi> a wiſe heart; and this was <hi>Salomons</hi> ſuite; <hi>An vnderstanding heart.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 3.9.</note> Hee ſaw, hee had power enough, but not wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome enough; and that Royaltie without wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, was no better then an eminent diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; a very Calfe made of golden Eare-rings. There is no Trade of life, but a peculiar wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome belongs to it; without which all is tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and vnprofitable: how much more to the higheſt and buſieſt vocation, the gouernment of men? An ignorant ruler is like a blind Pilot; who ſhall ſaue the veſſell from ruine?</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Cor patiens;</hi> a meeke heart: what is it to difcerne the cauſe, and not to bee patient of the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:23065:10"/>proceedings? The firſt Gouernour that God ſet ouer his Iſrael, was <hi>Moſes;</hi> a man of the meekeſt ſpirit vpon earth. How is hee fit to gouerne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that hath not learn'd to gouerne himſelfe? He that cannot rule a Boat on the riuer, is not to bee truſted with ſteering a Veſſell on the Ocean. Nor yet muſt this patience degenerate into co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlineſſe: <hi>Moſes</hi> that was ſo meeke in his owne cauſe, in Gods cauſe was as reſolute. So there is alſo</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Cor magnanimum,</hi> a heart of fortitude and courage. The rulers and ſquares that regulate others, are not made of lead or ſoft wood, ſuch as will bend or bow. The principall Columnes of a houſe, had need be heart of Oke. A timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and flexible Magiſtrate is not fit for theſe corrupt times. If either threatnings can terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him, or fauour melt him, or perſwaſions ſwerue him from Iuſtice, hee ſhall not want temptations. The Braine that muſt diſpell the fumes, aſcending from a corrupt liuer, ſtomach, or ſpleene, had need bee of a ſtrong conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The couragious ſpirit that reſolues to doe the will of heauen, what malignant powers ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer would croſſe it on earth, is the heart that God chuſeth.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly, there is <hi>Cor honeſtum,</hi> an honeſt heart. Without this, courage will prooue but legall Iniuſtice, policie but meere ſubtiltie, and abilitie but the Deuills Anuile to forge miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes. Priuate men haue many curbes; but men in authoritie, if they feare not God, haue
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:23065:10"/>nothing elſe to feare. If hee bee a ſimple Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard, hee feares all men: if a head-ſtrong com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, he feares no man; like that vniuſt Iudge, that <hi>feared neither God nor Man.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 18.2.</note> This is the ground of all fidelitie to King and Countrey, Religion. Such was <hi>Conſtantines</hi> Maxime; Hee cannot bee faithfull to mee, that is vnfaithfull to God. As this honourable place of the Kings Lieutena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t-ſhip hath a Sword bearer, ſo the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate himſelfe is the <hi>Lords Sword-bearer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> And as hee may neuer drawe this Sword in his priuate quarrell, ſo hee muſt not let it bee ſheathed when Gods cauſe calls for it. It is lenitie and conniuence that hath inuited con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to great places. Did Iuſtice carrie a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerer hand, they durſt not traduce their Rulers in Songs and Satyrs, the burden whereof will bee their owne ſhame. Magiſtrates are our ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill Fathers: and what deſerue they but the curſe of <hi>Cham,</hi> that lay open the nakedneſſe of <hi>their Fathers?</hi> When <hi>Alexander</hi> had conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Darius,</hi> and caſually found his ſlaine bodie lying naked, hee threw his owne coat ouer him, ſaying, I will couer the deſtinie of a King. It is God alone that <hi>caſteth contempt vpon Princes;</hi> which that hee may not doe, let them preſerue <hi>Cor mundum,</hi> a cleane heart, not conſcious of ill demerits.</p>
            <p>Such a one ſits on the Iudgement-Seat, as one that neuer forgets that hee muſt appeare before the Iudgement-Seate of Chriſt. So hee execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Iuſtice, as neuer loſing the ſenſe of Mercy:
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:23065:11"/>ſo hee ſheweth Mercie, as not offering violence to Iuſtice. Hee can at once, puniſh the offence, and pitie the offender. Hee remembers his oath, and feares to violate it: to an enemie hee is not cruell, to a friend hee will not bee partiall. And if euer hee haue but once cut the skirt of Iuſtice, as <hi>Dauid</hi> the lappe of <hi>Sauls</hi> garment, his <hi>Heart ſmites him</hi> for it. Hee minds no other clocke on the Bench, but that of his owne Conſcience. Hee will not offend the Iuſt, nor affoord a good looke to varlets: nor yet doth hee ſo diſregard their perſons, as to wrong their cauſes. Hee will maintaine Pietie, but not neglect Equitie. In Court, hee lookes not before him on the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nor about him on the beholders, nor behind him for bribes; nay, hee will not touch them in his Cloſſet or Chamber, leſt the timber and ſtones in the wall ſhould witneſſe againſt him. So hee helpes the Church, that the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth bee no loſer: ſo hee lookes to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, that the Church may not bee wronged. The lewd feare him, the good praiſe him, the poore bleſſe him; hee hath been a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Orphans, a Husband to diſtreſſed Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes. Many prayers are layde vp for him in Heauen; and when hee dies, they with the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of Angels, ſhall beare him vp to bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, let vs ſee why God will chuſe men by the heart. I denie not, but wiſedome and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, moderation and patience, are all requiſite concurrences: but the <hi>Heart</hi> is the <hi>Primum
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:23065:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Mobile,</hi> that ſets all the wheeles a going, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooues them to the right end. When God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to make a man good, he begins at the heart: as Nature in forming, ſo God in reforming, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins there. As the eye is the firſt that begins to die, and the laſt that begins to liue: ſo the heart is the firſt that liues, and the laſt that dies. It is ſaid of the Spider, that in the morning, before ſhee ſeekes out for her prey, ſhee mends her bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken webbe; and in doing that, ſhe alwayes begins in the midſt. Before wee purſue the profits and baits of this world, let vs firſt amend our life; and when wee vndertake this, let vs bee ſure to begin at the heart. The <hi>Heart</hi> is the Fort or Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tadell in this little Ile of man; let vs fortifie that, or all will bee loſt. And as naturally, the heart is firſt in being, ſo here the Will (which is meant by the Heart) is chiefe in commanding. The Centurions ſeruants did not more carefully o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey him, when hee ſayd to one <hi>Goe, and he goeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>to another Come, and hee commeth, to a third, Doe this, and hee doth it:</hi> then all the members ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the <hi>Heart;</hi> if it ſay to the eye, See, it ſeeth: to the eare, Heare, it hearkeneth: to the tongue, Speake, it ſpeaketh: to the foot, Walke, it wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth: to the hand, Worke, it worketh. If the <hi>Heart</hi> lead the way to God, not a member of the body, not a facultie of the ſoule, will ſtay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde. As when the Sunne ariſeth in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Birds riſe from their neſtes, Beaſtes from their dennes, and Men from their beds. They all ſay to the <hi>Heart,</hi> as the Iſraelites did to <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhuah;
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:23065:12"/>All that thou commandeſt vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſh. 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>wee will doe: and whither ſoeuer thou ſendeſt vs, wee will goe: onely the Lord bee with thee.</hi> Therefore the peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Publican <hi>ſmote his heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 18.13.</note> as if hee would call vp that, to call vp all the reſt. It cannot command and goe without.</p>
            <p>No part of man can ſinne without the heart, the heart can ſin without all the reſt. The Wolfe goes to the flocke, purpoſing to deuoure a Lambe, and is preuented by the vigilancie of the Shepheard; yet <hi>Lupus exit, Lupus regreditur;</hi> hee went foorth a Wolfe, and comes home a Wolfe. The heart intends a ſinne, which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer brought into action; yet it ſinnes in that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry intention. The hand cannot offend without the heart, the heart can offend without the hand. The heart is like a Mill: if the winde or water bee violent, the Mill will goe whether the Miller will or not; yet hee may chuſe what kind of graine it ſhall grind, wheat or darnell. If the affections bee ſtrong and paſſionate, the heart will bee working: yet the Chriſtian by grace, may keepe out luſtes, and ſupply it with good thoughts.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Heart</hi> is Gods peculiar; the thing hee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially cares for: <hi>My ſonne, giue mee thy heart:</hi> and good reaſon, for I gaue my owne Sonnes heart to death for it <hi>Non minus tuum, quia me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um;</hi> It is not leſſe thine, for being mine: yea, it cannot be thine comfortably, vnleſſe it bee mine perfectly. God requires it principally, but not onely: giue him that, and all the reſt will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:23065:12"/>He that giues me fire, needs not bee reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted for light and heat; for they are inſeparable. <hi>Non corticis, ſed cordis Deus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambr.</note> God doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the rinde of the lipps, but the root of the heart. It was the Oracles anſwere, to him that would bee inſtructed which was the beſt Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; <hi>Da medium Lunae, Solem ſimul, &amp; canis iram:</hi> which three characters make <hi>Cor,</hi> the Heart. Mans Affection is Gods <hi>Hall:</hi> mans Memorie, his <hi>Library:</hi> mans Intellect, his <hi>Priuie Chamber;</hi> but his Cloſſet, Sacrary, or Chappell, is the <hi>Heart.</hi> So Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> gloſſeth the <hi>Pater no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; Quies in coelis, which art in heauen,</hi> that is, in a heauenly <hi>Heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All outward workes an hypocrite may doe, onely hee failes in the Heart: and becauſe hee failes there, he is loſt euery where. Let the fleſh looke neuer ſo faire, the good Cater will not buy it, if the liuer bee ſpak'd. Who will put that timber into the building of his houſe, which is rotten at the heart? Man iudgeth the heart by the workes, God iudgeth the workes by the heart. All other powers of man may be ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from doing their offices, but onely the <hi>Will,</hi> that is the <hi>Heart.</hi> Therefore God will excuſe all neceſſary defects, but onely of the <hi>Heart.</hi> The blinde man cannot ſerue God with his eyes, hee is excuſed: the deafe cannot ſerue God with his eares, hee is excuſed: the dumbe cannot ſerue God with his tongue, hee is excuſed: the creeple cannot ſerue God with his feete, hee is excuſed. But no man is excuſed for not ſeruing
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:23065:13"/>God with his <hi>Heart. Deus non reſpicit quantum homo valet, ſed quantum velit.</hi> Saint <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome</hi> ſeemed to bee angrie with the Apoſtle, for ſaying,
<note place="margin">Math. 19.27.</note> 
               <hi>Behold, wee haue left all, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed thee.</hi> What haue you left? an angle, a couple of broken nettes, and a weather beaten Fiſh-boat; a faire deale to ſpeake of. But at laſt hee corrects himſelfe, <hi>I crie you mercie, Saint Peter:</hi> you haue <hi>forſaken all</hi> indeed: for he tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly leaues all, that leaues <hi>Quod vel capit mundus, vel cupit:</hi> that takes his <hi>Heart</hi> from the world, and giues it to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>All other faculties of man apprehend their obiects, when they are brought home to them; onely the Will, the Heart goes home to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect. Colour muſt come to the eye, before it can ſee it: ſound to the eare, before it can heare it: the obiect to bee apprehended is brought home to the vnderſtanding, and paſt things are recollected to the memory; before either can doe her office. But the heart goes home to the obiect. <hi>Vbi theſaurus, ibi cor.</hi> Not where the heart is, there will be the treaſure: but <hi>where the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is, there will be the heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bleſſed are the pure in heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>for they ſhall ſee God.</hi> Of all, the pure heart is beholding to God, and ſhall one day behold God. Therefore <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did</hi> prayes,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.10.</note> 
               <hi>Cor mundum crea in me, Deus: Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate in mee a cleane heart, O God.</hi> The Lord reſted from the workes of his Creation the ſeuenth day; but ſo dearely hee loues cleane hearts, that hee reſtes from creating them no day. As
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:23065:13"/>
               <hi>Iehu</hi> ſaid to <hi>Iehonadab, Eſt tibi cor rectum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 10.15</note> 
               <hi>Is thy heart right?</hi> Then giue mee thy hand, <hi>come vp into my charriot.</hi> So this is Gods queſtion, <hi>Is thy heart vpright?</hi> Then giue mee thy hand, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend my triumphant Charriot, the euerlaſting glory of heauen.</p>
            <p>To conclude; becauſe there is ſuch difference of hearts, and ſuch need of a good one; they put it to Him that knowes them all, and knowes which is beſt of all. For howſoeuer Nature knowes no difference; nor is there any <hi>Quorum praecordia Titan De meliore luto finxit:</hi> yet in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of grace, the ſanctified heart is of purer metall then common ones. A little liuing ſtone in Gods building, is worth a whole Quarrey of the world. One honeſt heart is better then a thouſand other: the richeſt Mine, and the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt mould, haue not ſuch a diſproportion of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue. Man often failes in his Election, God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not erre. The choiſe heere was extraordinary, by lots: yours is ordinary by Suffrages; Gods hand is in both.</p>
            <p>Great is the benefit of good Magiſtrates: that wee may ſit vnder our owne Vines, goe in and out in peace, eate our bread in ſaftie, and (which is aboue all) leade our liues in honeſt libertie: for all this wee are beholding, vnder God to the Magiſtrate, firſt the Supreme, then the ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate. They are Trees, vnder whoſe branches the people build and ſing, and bring vp their young ones in religious nourture. That <hi>Silence in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen about halfe an houre,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 8.</note> when the <hi>golden vialls
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:23065:14"/>were filled with ſweet odours,</hi> and the prayers of the Saints aſcended as pillars of ſmoke and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, is referred by ſome, to the peace of the Church vnder <hi>Conſtantine.</hi> It is the King of <hi>Mexico's</hi> Oath, when hee takes his Crowne; <hi>Iuſtitiam ſe adminiſtraturum, effecturum vt Sol curſum teneat, Nubes pluant, Rivi currant, terra producat fructus;</hi> that hee will miniſter Iuſtice, hee will make the Sunne holde his courſe, the Cloudes to raine, the Riuers to runne, and the Earth to fructifie. The meaning is, that the vpright and diligent adminiſtration of Iuſtice, will bring all theſe bleſſings of God vpon a Countrey.</p>
            <p>If wee compare this Citie with many in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine parts, how ioyfully may wee admire our owne happines! Thoſe murders and maſſacres, rapes and conſtuprations, and other miſchiefes, that bee there as common as nights, be rare with vs. I will not ſay that all our people are better then theirs, I dare ſay, our Gouernment is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then theirs. Merchants make higher vſe, and are more glad of calme Seas, then common paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers. So ſhould Chriſtians more reioyce in peace, then can the heathen: becauſe they know how to improoue it to richer ends, the glory of God, and ſaluation of their owne ſoules. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed yee graue and honourable Senatours, in your former approoued courſes, to the ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of vice and diſorders, and to the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Truth and Peace among vs. It is none of the leaſt renownes of this famous Citie, the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:23065:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>Wiſedome and Equitie of the Gouernours. To repeat the worthy acts done by the <hi>Lords Maters</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> were fitter for a Chronicle; they are too large for a Sermon.</p>
            <p>But it is high time to bleſſe you with a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and to diſmiſſe you with a Bleſſing. That Almightie God, <hi>that knowes the hearts of all,</hi> ſanctifie your hearts to gouerne, and ours to obey; that wee all ſeeking to doe good one to another, <hi>He</hi> may doe good vnto vs all. To this bleſſed and eternall God, the Father, the Sonne, and the Holy Ghoſt, bee all glory and praiſe for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
